Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching: Classification Project M1836
Dept. of Special Collections & University Archives
Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching: Classification Project
1973-2007
M1836
Dept. of Special Collections & University Archives
11.0 Linear feet (12 boxes, 4 cartons)
Contains correspondence and intstitutional information re. Classification Project at Carnegie.
Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching.
McCormick, Alexander C
Access to Collection
Open for research. Born-digital materials in cartons 13-16 (computer tapes, floppy disk) are CLOSED until processed.
Biographical/Historical note
The Carnegie Classification has been the leading framework for recognizing and describing institutional diversity in U.S. higher education for the past four decades. Starting in 1970, the Carnegie Commission on Higher Education developed a classification of colleges and universities to support its program of research and policy analysis. Derived from empirical data on colleges and universities, the Carnegie Classification was originally published in 1973, and subsequently updated in 1976, 1987, 1994, 2000, 2005, and 2010 to reflect changes among colleges and universities. This framework has been widely used in the study of higher education, both as a way to represent and control for institutional differences, and also in the design of research studies to ensure adequate representation of sampled institutions, students, or faculty.
Acquisition Information
This collection was given by the Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching to Stanford University, Special Collections in September 2011.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains correspondence, meeting notes, agreements, miscellaneous information on various institutions involved in the project, and Alex McCormick's notebooks and phone logs documenting the project. Born-digital materials contained on computer tapes in cartons 13-16 have not been processed and are not yet available.
Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching.; Classification; Degrees, Academic; Education, Higher.; Educational research; Universities and colleges
- Correspondence, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1990 (January) (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1990 (February-December) (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Memoranda, 1991-1994 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Memoranda, 1995-1997 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Memorandum: Classification Forward, March 4, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Correspondence/Memoranda: College Faculty survey, 1991-1996 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Memoranda: 1994 Classification Development (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Memoranda: Classification Changes, 1994-1997 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- 1973 & 1976 Classification (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Classification: Definitions of Types of Institutions (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Classification changes, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Name changes in classification, 1975-1991 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Classification changes, openings & closings (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Institutions with no Carnegie classification (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Institutions reclassified between 1987 & 1994 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- "A Classification of Institutions of Higher Education," November 1993 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- 1994 Data Run (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Classification changes, ca. 1995 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Selectivity Scale, 1989-1994 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Selectivity Scale, 1989-1994 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Signed license agreements, 1987-1995 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Signed license agreements, 1987-1995 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Signed license agreements, 1987-1995 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- John Minter: classification adjustments, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- NSF obligations (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Classifications Advisory Committee, 1987-1990 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Classifications Advisorty Meetings, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Washington Higher Education Secreterial (WHES) Mtg, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Preliminary classficiation schemes/codes, 2003 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Research materials: outline/statistics for classification paper, 2003 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Research materials: outline/statistics for classification paper, 2003-2004 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Classification tabulation, ca. 2005 (?) (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Classification progress reports, 2005-2006 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Alex McCormick notebook, ca. 2000 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Alex McCormick notebooks, Classification 1&2 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Alex McCormick notebook, Classification special meetings, 2004 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Alex McCormick notebook, publications & conferences, 2001-2007 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Alex McCormick notebook, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Alex McCormick, phone logs, Jan 1999-April 1999 (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Alex McCormick phone logs, December 1992-Sept. (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Alex McCormick, phone logs, November 2000- August (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Alex McCormick, phone logs, August 2004- February (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Alex McCormick, phone logs, March 2007- December (Box 6, Folder 4)
- ClassificationsCE 2005: Survey monkey (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Laguardia Community College- Pilot application Only/Never Applied for CLA (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Community Engagement Elective: Summary pf institutions,2005 (Box 6, Folder 7)
- CE Classifications 2005: Correspondence/ Follow up with institutions from which no application was recieved (Box 6, Folder 8)
- CE Classifications 2005: Correspondence/ Institutions not invited to apply (Box 6, Folder 9)
- CE Classifications 2005: Correspondence/ Letters indicating withdrawl (Box 6, Folder 10)
- CE Classifications 2005: Correspondence / letter of intent (Box 7, Folder 1)
- CE Classifications 2005: Permissions Responses (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Allegheny College (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Antioch University New England (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Arizona State University at the Tempe Campus (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Bates College (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Boise State University (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Bowling Green State University- Main Campus (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Bristol Community College (Box 7, Folder 9)
- Bryn Mawr College (Box 7, Folder 10)
- California State University - Chico (Box 7, Folder 11)
- California State University - Fresno (Box 7, Folder 12)
- California State University - Monterey Bay (Box 7, Folder 13)
- California State University - San Marcos (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Chandler / Gilbert Community College (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Depaul University (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Elon University (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Emory University (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Gettysburg College (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Indiana State University (Box 8, Folder 7)
- Indiana University - Purdue University - Indianapolis (Box 8, Folder 8)
- Kapiolani Community College (Box 8, Folder 9)
- Keene State College (Box 8, Folder 10)
- Kent State University - Main Campus (Box 8, Folder 11)
- Madonna University (Box 8, Folder 12)
- Michigan State University (Box 8, Folder 13)
- Middlebury College (Box 9, Folder 1)
- Middlesex Community College (Box 9, Folder 2)
- Morehead State University (Box 9, Folder 3)
- New York University (Box 9, Folder 4)
- North Carolina State University at Raleigh (Box 9, Folder 5)
- Northern Kentucky University (Box 9, Folder 6)
- Oklahoma State University - Main Campus (Box 9, Folder 7)
- Otis College of Art and Design (Box 9, Folder 8)
- Pace University- New York (Box 9, Folder 9)
- Pitzer College (Box 9, Folder 10)
- Portland State University (Box 9, Folder 11)
- Rhodes College (Box 9, Folder 12)
- Richland College (Box 9, Folder 13)
- Rockford College (Box 9, Folder 14)
- Rutgers University - Newark (Box 9, Folder 15)
- Saint Thomas Aquinas College (Box 9, Folder 16)
- San Francisco State University (Box 9, Folder 17)
- Santa Clara University (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Spelman College (Box 10, Folder 2)
- Syracuse University (Box 10, Folder 3)
- Texas Tech University (Box 10, Folder 4)
- Trinity College (Box 10, Folder 5)
- Tufts University (Box 10, Folder 6)
- Tusculum College (Box 10, Folder 7)
- University of Alaska Anchorage (Box 10, Folder 8)
- University of Baltimore (Box 10, Folder 9)
- University of Cincinnati - Main Campus (Box 10, Folder 10)
- University of Denver (a) (Box 10, Folder 11)
- University of Denver, cont. (Box 11, Folder 1)
- University of Kentucky (Box 11, Folder 2)
- University of Massachusetts - Boston (Box 11, Folder 3)
- University of Memphis (Box 11, Folder 4)
- University of Minnesota - Twin Cities (Box 11, Folder 5)
- University of Nebraska at Omaha (Box 11, Folder 6)
- University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill (Box 11, Folder 7)
- University of North Dakoka - Main Campus (Box 11, Folder 8)
- University of Northern Iowa (Box 11, Folder 9)
- University of Pennsylvania (Box 11, Folder 10)
- University of Redlands (Box 11, Folder 11)
- University of San Diego (Box 11, Folder 12)
- University of San Francisco (Box 11, Folder 13)
- University of South Florida (Box 11, Folder 14)
- University of St. Thomas (Box 12, Folder 1)
- University of Vermont and State Agricultural College (Box 12, Folder 2)
- University of Wisconsin- Parkside (Box 12, Folder 3)
- Virginia Commonwealth University (Box 12, Folder 4)
- Virginia Polytechnich Institute and State University (Box 12, Folder 5)
- Wartburg College (Box 12, Folder 6)
- Western Kentucky University (Box 12, Folder 7)
- Widener University - Main Campus (Box 12, Folder 8)
- Winona State University (Box 12, Folder 9)
- Classification/Survey reel-to-reel magnetic back-up tapes (10) (Carton 13)
  Access note
  These materials are CLOSED until processed.
- Classification/Survey reel-to-reel magnetic back-up tapes (12) (Carton 14)
- Classification/Survey reel-to-reel magnetic back-up tapes (11) (Carton 15)
- Classification/Survey reel-to-reel magnetic back-up tapes (12); 1 floppy zip disk: Carnegie Fac. Surveys (1969, 1975, 1984, 1997) from Jack Schuster & Marty Finkelstein, 2001 (Carton 16)